Leah: We have touched on this already,
but all organisations that work with
children and young people should have
procedures and policies of safeguarding
in place to ensure that every child,
regardless of age, disability, gender
reassignment, race, religion or
belief, sex or sexual orientation
has an equal protection from harm.
Rhiannon: They should also be safe
from other children or adults who may
present a risk, wherever they are.
Abuse can potentially occur anywhere,
from voluntary, community or faith
groups, schools, hospitals and
sports clubs and even in the home.
Leah: Specific safeguarding issues,
with children and young people
include, bullying, self-harm,
criminal exploitation, sexual
exploitation, grooming, domestic
abuse, drug exploitation and county
lines activities, radicalisation,
up skirting and sexting, forced
marriage, FGM and honour based abuse.
Rhiannon: As many as 1 in 3 children
sexually abused by an adult, never
tell anyone, so it's crucial that even
those who only occasionally work with
children, should be aware of safeguarding
and child protection and what to do.
Leah: If a person suspects that any
safeguarding issues have arisen, they
should record any information they can
and tell someone who can report it.
This could be a friend, a
teacher, a family member, a social
worker, a doctor or healthcare
professional, a police officer or
someone else who can be trusted.
Rhiannon: All children and young
people should be listened to and
not dismissed, but their rights also
need to be respected and situations
need to be handled sensitively and
appropriately by the proper authorities.